Finding Aid for Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records 1956-1998, 1985-1997
University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.
69 linear feet
921070 Bimu C565 2
The information Technology Division, formed in 1985, consolidated academic and administrative computing at the University of Michigan. Douglas Van Houweling was named head of the unit and at the same time appointed to the new position of Vice Provost for Information Technology. During the 1980s, the unit oversaw a shift away from Michigan Terminal System (MTS) mainframe computing to a distributed, networked environment. The Information Technology Division record group documents the development of networked computing at the University of Michigan as it evolved from 1979 to 1995, mainly during the tenure of Douglas Van Houweling. The records include historical data, internal and external committee material, correspondence, and topical files and visual material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Information Technology Division (Donor No. 7873 ) in several accessions beginning in July 1990.
The Information Technology Division records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Information Technology Division record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 52
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 58-66
Computer Sales Program -- Box 58
Computing Sites -- Boxes 58-60
Dean's Partnership Program -- Box 61
Divisions -- Boxes 62-65
Software and Vendors -- Box 66
Early in 1985, Douglas Van Houweling was appointed to the new position of Vice Provost for Information Technology. Later that year he was named head of a newly formed unit, Information Technology Division (ITD), consolidating academic and administrative computing services at the University of Michigan. By the end of the 1990s, ITD's function had evolved into managing complex computer networking and telecommunication systems while providing leadership in the innovative application of information technology in higher education.
The management of computing resources at the university and the structure of ITD underwent a number of changes and reorganizations through the years concurrent with, and in response to, rapidly changing technology. Prior to 1985, oversight of campus computing activities fell under several jurisdictions. The Academic Computing Center reported to the Vice President for Academic Affairs (VPAA) while the Data Systems Center was a unit of the Office of Administrative Systems under the Vice President for Finance. The University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (UCCPU), established in 1965, was the primary advisory committee to the VPAA on computing issues. The committee coordinated policy among the units and also reviewed all significant computer acquisitions. With the creation of ITD, the UCCPU was disbanded in 1985.
The Computing Policy Committee (CPC), originally proposed in 1984, was established in 1985 as the primary advisory committee to the Vice Provost for Information Technology. Its function was to recommend and review long-range policies for computing, in the broadest sense and covering all parts of the university, and to review budget allocations for computing and information technology. The committee was chaired by the VP for Information Technology; members included the deputy vice provost and director of the computing center, director of administrative systems, director of the University Library, associate director of the University Hospital, eight faculty, two administrators, and (later) two students.
In 1987 it was determined that a single committee could not effectively address both planning and policy issues. The Computing Policy Committee was disbanded and its planning and policy functions divided between the newly created Information Technology General Council (ITGC) and the Information Technology Policies Committee (ITPC). An Executive Computing Committee, comprised of the Vice Provost for Information Technology, Vice President for Academic Affairs, Vice President and Chief Financial Officer, and Vice President for Research, was made responsible for overall supervision of information technology on campus.
ITD's administrative structure by 1994 included a number of divisions: Computing Center, Office of Administrative Systems (both of which predated ITD), Center for Information Technology Integration, Consulting and Support Services, Instructional Technology Systems, Network Systems, Research Systems, Resource Administration, and University Information Systems.
The Computing Center, established in 1959 as the Academic Computing Center, managed the mainframe computers and provided users with tutorial support and access to terminals, microcomputers, line and laser printers, electronic mail and conferencing systems, network access, and other advanced information technology. In the mid-1960s, Computing Center research staff developed the Michigan Terminal System (MTS) as the operating system on the International Business Machines (IBM) system 360 model 66m, the first university computer with online capabilities. MTS provided a high quality, centralized, interactive facility for time-shared computing that formed the foundation of campus computing activity for two decades.
During the 1980s, two major trends in computing emerged at the university that required a reevaluation of the university's computing resources. First, there was a shift away from mainframe computing to distributed computing, and second, the number of new computer users within the university community increased dramatically. In response to the demands of these new users, the Computing Center introduced new services and equipment, such as public workstations, applications software, and microcomputer education, and began exploring new operating systems as possible alternatives to MTS.
The Office of Administrative Systems (OAS) was divided into five subdivisions: the Data Systems Center, Information Systems Services, Telecommunications Systems, Administrative Support, and Systems Security. The OAS was responsible for "providing information systems containing university data, providing large-scale integrated databases for central administrative functions, and assisting units and individuals with the creation and use of their own systems for administrative computing." The two major projects of the OAS in the mid 1980s were the design and implementation of a new, centralized online admissions system, and the development of UMTel, a new university telecommunications system. The Research Systems, Center for Information Technology Integration, and Instructional Technology divisions undertook significant in-house and collaborative research including software development and testing, educational applications, and development of the Institutional File System.
The Computing Center and ITD were involved early in the development and operation of computer networks. The Merit Computer Network, based at the University of Michigan, was initiated as an educational, inter-university network linking several of Michigan's public universities. Proposals for a network linking the state's major universities were first made in 1964. In 1966, Wayne State, Michigan State, and University of Michigan formed Merit Inc., a non-profit corporation, to develop and manage the network. Development funds were obtained in 1969 from a state appropriation and a National Science Foundation Grant; the network became operational in 1972. Since that time, numerous public and private institutions joined the network. In 1984/1985, the Merit staff and the communications staff of the Computing Center, which oversaw UMNet (the local branch of Merit), were merged. Douglas Van Houweling was named chairman of the Board of Directors of Merit, and Bertram Herzog was selected as the first director in 1968. Eric Aupperle succeeded him in 1974. In 1987 Merit, in partnership with IBM and MCI, won the contract to develop and operate the National Science Foundation's national network backbone, NSFNET, connecting the six NSF supercomputing sites and numerous regional networks and university computing centers. ITD also hosted CICNet, a network linking members of the Committee on Institutional Cooperation, essentially the Big Ten universities and the University of Chicago.
Phase out of MTS, the heart of the university's academic computing system for more than two decades, began in the late 1980s. ITD was redefined to focus on network development and orienting users to a networked environment, while further integrating academic and administrative computing on campus. Gregory Marks, as deputy vice provost for information technology, managed much of the overall internal administration of this evolution from the mid 1980s through the mid 1990s. Van Houweling, functioning as vice provost for information technology and named in 1995 to the newly created post of dean for academic outreach, continued to be involved in a broad array of organizations at the national level, serving on numbers of government, corporate and academic advisory boards and panels.
In 1996, Van Houweling left ITD to become president and chief executive officer of the University Corporation for Advanced Internet Development (UCAID), a consortium of more then 100 universities working with corporate partners and federal agencies to develop Internet2. Jose(-Marie Griffiths was named executive director of ITD and chief information officer for the university. Early in her leadership, she reduced mid-level management and targeted ITD's focus on areas involving direct interaction with customers. In 1999, Griffiths was appointed to the National Research Council (NRC) Computer Science and Telecommunications Board's project on information technology strategy for the Library of Congress. In the same year, she announced the creation of a "'federation' of university information technology organizations to better plan and manage the University's information technology infrastructure and services.1" Griffith charged the newly formed Federation Executive Committee with the responsibility of identifying resources and needs across the university. Griffith's tenure as the second chief information officer ended in 2001. Her departure closed the door on the position of the chief information officer at the university. Instead, two newly formed organizations, Michigan Administrative Information Services (MAIS) and Information Technology Central Services (ITCS) have the responsibility for all aspects of computing at the university. MAIS reports to the office of the executive vice president and chief financial officer and has five core functions, management of three administrative systems Financial, Human Resources, and Student Administration; Integrated Information Delivery; Technical Infrastructure Operation; and User Consulting. Information Technology Central Services reports to the associate provost for academic, information and instructional technology affairs and supports five core divisions, Information Technology Communications Services (ITCS), University of Michigan Computing Environment (UMCE), User Advocate, User Services, and Web Applications, Technologies, and Solutions (WATS).
Commonly Used Acronyms in the Information Technology Division Record Group
CAEN -- Computer Aided Engineering Network
CITI -- Center for Information Technology Integration
ECC -- Executive Computing Committee
FCE -- Future Computing Environment
FTP -- File Transfer Protocol
IFS -- Institutional File System
ITPC -- Information Technology Policies Committee
ITAC -- Information Technology Architecture Committee
ITGC -- Information Technology General Counsel
MERIT -- Michigan Education and Research Information Triad
MPP -- Massively Parallel Processing
MTS -- Michigan Terminal System
NUBS -- North University Building Station
OSF -- Open Software Foundation
ResComp -- Residential Hall Computing
TQM -- Total Quality Management
SIGLABS -- Special Interest Group in Labs
UNYN -- Michigan Union Computing Site
Records of the Information Technology Division were received in several accessions between 1994 and 1996 with a smaller accession in 2001. Physical arrangement of the records reflects the order in which the records were received in multiple accessions. Within each accession, the records are organized in series, some of which continue between accessions and which may temporally overlap
In this finding aid, the intellectual organization of the records is given priority and like series from the various accessions are brought together. As a result, in the detailed container list the box numbers will not always follow sequentially.
The records of the Information Technology Division measure 23.5 linear feet and date from 1976 to1998; the bulk of the material represents the years 1985 to 1997. The records consist of correspondence, meeting minutes, electronic mail, newspaper clippings, and reports. They document the administration of ITD, the development of computing on campus, UM's role in the development and management of local, regional, and national computer networks, and ITD's participation, largely in the person of Douglas Van Houweling, in a number of computing organizations, most notably EDUCOM and CIESIN (Consortium for International Earth Science Information Network).
The ITD record group is divided into fourteen series including Central Files, Divisions, Networks, University Files, Vendors, Organizations, Deputy Vice-Provost for Information Technology, Vice-Provost for Information Technology, Virginia Rezmerski Files, Computer Sales Program, Computing Sites, Dean's Partnership Program, Software, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Computers.; University of Michigan. Information Technology Division.; Van Houweling, Douglas E.; Marks, Gregory, 1939-; Michigan Terminal System.; University of Michigan. Vice-Provost for Information Technology.; Merit Network, Inc.; International Business Machines Corporation.; Computer networks.; Information technology.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Aupperle, Eric M.; Autrey-Hunley, Carolyn.; Bartels, R. C. F. (Robert Christian Frank); Van Houweling, Douglas E.; University of Michigan. Computing Center.; Computers.; International Business Machines Corporation.; Michigan Terminal System.; Educom.; University of Michigan--Congresses.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs)
- Central Files 1984-1997
  The Central Files series (12.5 linear ft., 1984-1997) is the main administrative file of the division. It is organized into two subseries, 1984-1992 and 194-1997, reflecting different accessions. Each subseries is organized in a number of sub-subseries including: Historical Files, Audit records, Budgets, Committees-ITD, Committees-University-Wide, Correspondence and Topical file.
  - 1984-1992
    Historical files are mainly news clippings featuring computing at the University of Michigan and organizational charts for 1985 to 1991. Audits include thorough reports on 1985 to 1987 external audits of ITD operations (including ITD responses) and a 1991 ITD response to an internal audit. There is also some information on a Medical Information Systems audit. (Note: The subseries does not include records on the 1992/93 audit following allegations of ITD overcharges to federally sponsored projects.) Budgets, 1985 to 1991, include correspondence and reports on the ITD budget process, as well as some background information.
    The Committees sub-subseries is further divided into ITD Committees and University-wide committees. Files of the Computing Policy Committee (CPC), Information Technology General Council (ITGC), Information Technology Policies Committee (ITPC), and Executive Computing Committee (ECC) provide the broadest overview of campus information technology issues and are among the most significant. Also important are the files of the Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC), formed in 1986 to provide the functional and broad technical specifications for the systems implemented by ITD over the next several years, and the Strategic Planning Committee files. The latter include minutes, Van Houweling's notes, and drafts of the 1989 report "Strategic Directions for Information Technology at the University of Michigan." The Senior Managers Committee files, which include minutes of monthly meetings and several retreats, offer the best source on internal management of ITD.
    Topical files are arranged alphabetically. Significant files include Grants, ITD Vision Statement, MEET:STUDENTS Computer Conference, Policy Statements, Supercomputers, and Van Houweling. Grant files provide examples of the types of projects encouraged and supported by ITD, promoting the educational use of information technology. The ITD Vision statement file consists of notes for a 1990 presentation by Van Houweling. MEET:STUDENTS records document the controversy over the appearance of allegedly racist and sexist comments in the "Bad Joke" item of an ITD sponsored computer conference. Included is the text of the item, correspondence, memoranda and a printout of a discussion about the controversy from online discussion in the MEET:PLANNERS computer conference. The MEET:PLANNERS discussion raises issues of free speech, acceptable behavior on computer conferences and ITD’s response to the controversy.
    Policy Statements contain a number of ITD policies on the use of computing facilities including: "Conditions of Use," "Proper Use of Information Resources," "Information Technology and Networks," and "Guidelines for Interaction with Corporate Representatives.” There is also a small file on ITD policy relating to Freedom of Information Act Requests. (Note: The records do not include files on the 1992 to 1994 FOIA requests arising from a controversy over access to private computer conferences.) The Supercomputer files document ITD’s unsuccessful bid to become host for one of six NSF supercomputing sites in 1986. The Van Houweling files include biographical material, resumes, a May 1989 interview transcript and two folders of speeches and articles.
    Other files of interest in Topical Files include material on ITD’s 1989 reorganization and Research Resources, a printout describing resources of the Computing Center and resources available in various colleges and departments. The last of these includes an overview of the development of computing at Michigan and describes the machines, programs, and services available in 1985.
    - Historical Materials
      - General (Box 1)
      - "Meeting the Campus Networking Challenge," 1987 (Box 1)
        (paper by Gregory Marks for an EDUCOM publication)
      - Organizational charts 1985-1991 (Box 1)
    - Audits
      - 1985-1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1991 (Box 1)
    - Budgets
      - 1985-1991, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Committees (ITD)
      - Ad-Hoc Committee on Advancing Use of Information Technology 1987 (Box 1)
      - Budget Planning Process Group (BPPG)
        - 1991 (Box 1)
        - 1992 (ITD-1993 and Beyond Committee) (Box 1)
      - Combined Operations Task Group 1986 (Box 1)
      - Computing Policy Committee
        - 1984 (proposal for establishing committee) (Box 1)
        - 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Executive Computing Committee
        - 1985-1992, 7 folders (Box 1)
      - Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC)
        - 1986-1987 (Formative Committee) (Box 1)
        - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
        - WITAC 1987-1988 (Box 1)
      - Information Technology General Council (ITGC)
        - Correspondence, Minutes, etc.
          - 1987-1992, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - IT Clipboard, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
      - Information Technology Personnel Programs and Services Advisory Group 1986 (Box 2)
      - Information Technology Policies Committee (ITPC)
        - Correspondence 1991-1992 (Box 2)
        - Minutes, Agendas etc. 1988-1992, 12 folders (Box 2)
      - Mid-Managers Meetings 1990 (Box 2)
      - Projects/Planning Meeting Minutes
        - 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Senior Managers
        - 1987, 4 folders (Box 2)
        - 1987 November Retreat (Box 2)
        - 1988-1992, 13 folders (Box 3)
        - 1990 March Retreat (Box 3)
        - 1990 October Retreat (Box 3)
      - Selection Committee (software and hardware) 1985, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Strategic Planning Committee
        - 1985 (Box 3)
          (Van Houweling notes on strategic choices)
        - 1987-1988 (Box 3)
          (minutes, correspondence etc.)
        - Report drafts ("Strategic Directions for Information Technology at the University of Michigan," preliminary plan) 1989 (Box 3)
      - TQM (Total Quality Management) Task Force August-November, 1991 (Box 3)
      - TQM Council 1992 (Box 3)
      - Working Groups on Information Technology 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - Committees (University-wide)
      - Academic Affairs Advisory Committee 1991-1992 (Box 4)
        (includes Van Houweling notes from meeting on sexual orientation issues)
      - Budget Priorities Committee 1990-1992, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
        (e-mail printouts)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 4)
    - Topical File
      - Affirmative Action 1985 (Box 4)
      - Computer Kickoff
        - 1987 (Box 4)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 4)
      - Computer Mediated Simulation (Tanter, Political Science) 1987 (Box 4)
      - Computerized Academic Record Project 1988 (Box 4)
      - Computing Fees 1987 (Box 4)
      - Development Office Proposal 1987 (Box 4)
      - Diversity/Sexual Harassment 1987-1990 (Box 4)
      - Gaming and Simulation 1986 (Box 4)
      - Gehrung Associates (Walt Harrison) 1988 (Box 4)
      - Grants (by ITD)
        - General 1985-1987 (Box 4)
        - Educational Initiative Grants 1985-1987
          - Allen, Layman, "Thinkers League" (Box 4)
          - Brown, CRLT (Center for Research on Learning and Teaching) (Box 4)
          - Bryant, SNR (School of Natural Resources) (Box 4)
          - Dumas, Nursing (Box 4)
          - Feldt, Architecture & Urban Planning (Box 4)
          - Goodman, Education (Box 4)
          - Holland, Engineering Library (Box 4)
          - Johnston, ISR (video case study) (Box 4)
          - Kleinsmith, Biology (Box 4)
          - Kozma, Education "The Learning Tree" (Box 4)
        - Impact Grants 1985-1987
          - General (Box 4)
          - Kleinsmith, Biology
            - Stewart, Art (Box 4)
            - Jessup, LS&A (Box 4)
          - Matching Grants 1985-1987
            - General (Box 4)
            - Bentley Library (Box 4)
            - Business Administration (Box 4)
            - Dental School (Box 4)
            - DRDA (Box 5)
            - Engineering (Box 5)
            - Literature, Science & the Arts (Box 5)
            - Music (Box 5)
            - Natural Resources (Box 5)
            - Pharmacy (Box 5)
            - Physics (Box 5)
            - Social Work (Box 5)
        - Infonet (EDUCOM meeting, 1989) (Box 5)
        - ITD LAN Project Proposal 1989 (Box 5)
        - ITD Vision Statement 1990 (Box 5)
          (Van Houweling speech notes?)
        - "Information Technology, Status and Plans" (Box 5)
          (notes and charts for a presentation, December 1986)
        - Integrated Technology Instructional Center (ITIC) 1987 (Box 5)
        - Intellectual Property (Box 5)
        - Local Vendors/Computer Sales 1988 (Box 5)
        - Local Area Networks 1987 (Box 5)